[Music]
Stanford
University all right let's um talk about
rotations of space in this language
rotations of space are
asymmetry and they can act on various
things but one of the things they can
act on is vectors those vectors might be
a vector field or they might just be
some uh some Vector in space a velocity
Vector whatever
uh rotations act on
vectors and they rotate vectors from one
vector to another no we can put this
up rotations can be combined you can
take an object rotate it about an axis
by a certain angle and then rotate it by
another axis about an angle and the
result is an overall rotation about some
other axis by some other angle
so in an abstract sense uh the rotations
do form a group let's just think about
it for a minute the rotation operations
have a group
structure
[Music]
um imagine taking a set of
coordinates incidentally how do we
parameterize
rotations rotations can be parameterized
as
vectors all right we won't won't worry
about the fact that rotating by more
than for the Moment by more than 2 pi
brings you back to this so supposing you
won't don't worry about that for a
moment rotations can be first of all
they have an axis they're rotations
about an axis let's take all rotations
to always be
right-handed in other words rotations
right-handed what happens if we have a
rotation which is
Left-Handed we can either think of it as
a rotation a right-handed Rotation by
negative angle
or we can think of it as a right-handed
Rotation by the opposite axis doesn't
matter you get the same thing all right
so rotation has an axis let's call that
a unit Vector
n and it has an angle that you rotate by
okay
Theta how many parameters does it take
to describe an angle a unit
Vector takes two parameters to describe
a unit vector longitude and latitude on
the sphere unit Vector is a an arrow
pointing on to a unit sphere so that's
two angles and another angle for how
much you rotate about that's three
angles or three parameters to describe a
rotation it's a three parameter family
of objects now when you rotate an object
if you rotate an object a rigid object
imagine you have a rigid object and you
rotate it about some axis and then you
rotate it about some other axis the
result is
always equivalent to a rotation by yet
some other axis and some other angle so
the product of two rotations one done
sequentially one and then another is
always another rotation so the answer is
yes uh there is a product structure to
rotations number one there is an
identity operation for rotations just no
rotation at all there is an inverse
any rotation about any axis the inverse
of it is just the rotation by the
opposite angle about the same Axis or
you can if you like think of it the same
rotation about the opposite axis but
let's not get into that there's always
for any rotation about any axis there's
always exactly the opposite one which
undoes it so there's an inverse
structure sorry there's a yeah there's
an inverse structure what else do we
need for a group
associative it is and it also happens to
be associative yeah it happens to be
associative uh that that's a true fact
it's not quite as
obvious okay so rotations are a group uh
have we failed to say anything about
rotations oh good it's non ailion this
is the fact that a rotation about the
x-axis followed by a rotation about the
y axis is not the same as interchanging
the two orders of rotation go home and
do that if you haven't done it before
rotate about the x- axis then the y axis
and then do it in the opposite order you
won't get back to the same thing the
smaller the rotations are the closer it
is to being a bilon
yes sequential rotations not
simultaneous no no sequential one after
another yeah group action is always
corresponds to sequ sequential uh
right
right that is correct the the smaller
the rotations in a certain sense the uh
the closer it is to commuting but the
group is definitely a non-commutative or
nonabelian group it's our first
nonabelian
group let's uh talk about its
representations where we're going
incidentally is if we get to it tonight
is the study of
color color is a symmetry group and it's
represented as a symmetry the color of
I'm talking now not about the the color
of your shirt I'm talking about the
color of quarks the red green and blue
it's not up and down it's not a
two-state system it's a three-state
system and the operations which uh which
are interesting are the ones which mix
up the different colors of
quirks and but so much of physics has
that pattern of uh of group group
symmetries that we need to understand it
before we go on okay um
rotations rotations how do we construct
a representation a matrix representation
of rotations and the easiest way to do
it is to take the components of a
vector let the basic objects be the
components of an ordinary
Vector caller vector v
and it has components VX Y and Z or
VI let's call them
VI I can equal 1 2 and 3 or X Y and Z
and so forth now when you rotate either
you can either think of rotating the
axes or rotating physically the vector
about some direction of course the
components VX and VY and VZ change and
they change by being multiplied by a
rotation Matrix
all right so for every rotation about
any angle about any axis there is a
rotation
Matrix the rotation Matrix depends on
the angle of rotation and the
axis and it is a matrix i
j how do you find the new resulting set
of components you multiply the matrix by
VJ and you get let's call it V Prime
I again summed over J this is Matrix
times Vector gives transformed
Vector all right that well these are
rotation matrices now
this do you know the definition do you
know the um the properties of rotation
matrices I believe we've gone through
them but I will go through them
again
uh h invariant L invariant length yeah
let's just see what that
says yeah let's uh let's work out the
properties of rotation
matrices this is another group of course
another group and another
representation this is a
threedimensional
representation of the rotation group it
is not the only representation of the
rotation
group uh there's many of them but this
is the threedimensional 3X3 Matrix
representation the rotation group and
it's easy to think about because you can
just visualize it in terms of the
components of a three Vector of a
spatial
Vector all right
um if R rotates V and gives V Prime and
R is truly a rotation of a vector then
it doesn't change the length of the
vector that's the property of a rotation
it changes nobody's length incidentally
we take the components of the vector to
be real numbers for the moment real
numbers and the matrices R are also
composed out of real
elements okay so what is the condition
the condition is the condition for this
to be a rotation is that for every
possible
V and V Prime V Prime being the result
of rotation that vi
vi this means the sum vx2 + V y^2 + vz^
2 the length the square of the length of
V should be the same as the square of
the length of V
Prime let's work that out let's see what
that says we can work that out in detail
this is r i
j let's let's put VJ here doesn't matter
we're summing it doesn't matter what we
call call it VJ same thing uh okay r i j
v j is equal to V Prime I right oh I
don't know maybe it's maybe I want that
I here doesn't matter this is V Prime I
right let's write the same equation
again r i k v k equals V Prime I
I've changed I you
never this dummy index the summation
index I don't want to conflate with this
one here but this one is the same as
this
one now what I want to do is I want to
form V Prime i v Prime I so I want to
multiply this by this and Su over I and
what will I get I will get V Prime
i v Prime I equals r i j
VJ r i k
VK with every repeated index summed
over or equivalently just uh write it a
little differently r i j r i
k VJ
VK
this should be the same as what this
should be the same as vi
vi right
that's this over here is equal to this
over
here what is the condition that this is
equal to this for every possible
V right all right let's write it in two
steps uh it is that r i j r i k is equal
to Delta J K in other words if this were
true that r i j r i k sum over I was the
chronica Delta then it would tell you to
set J equal to
K and this would just become
v^2 so that's the condition for a
rotation
Matrix and it can be written in a
different way it can be written that uh
that the uh transpose R time times
transpose is equal to one this is the
unit operator and this is the
representation for R * its
transpose so a ation Matrix satisfies
let's write over
here that
R transpose time
R is equal to one does everybody
remember what transpose is transpose is
just interchanging rows in
columns R transpose R is equal to
1 now actually we immediately now know
what the inverse of any rotation Matrix
is it's just a
transpose okay
the rotation group has this property
that and that's B that's basically its
defining property R trans that's the
defining property of the matrices of
rotation
matrices if you construct for every
rotation such a matrix and you multiply
the matrices you will find the the um
the the Matrix representation of the
multiplication table of uh of
rotations I'm just doing this as an
example
uh so there are 3x3 representations
threedimensional representations of the
rotation
group can we think of the
three-dimensional representations of the
rotation group as in any way being
related to the quantum states of
something well we've studied spin
spin describes uh the angular momentum
of a particle and so forth and you can
rotate the spin of a particle you can
take a particle and you can rotate it
you can put it in the magnetic field
rotate the magnetic field and it'll mix
up the states it'll mix up the
states uh we discovered that there were
various angular momentum possibilities
for the spin there will spin a half spin
one spin three halves it also spin zero
spin zero spin a half spin one how many
states does a spin one particle
have
three what happens when you take the
state of a and what does that mean that
means that a spin one particle just the
spin of it nothing but the spin of it
can be described by a column Vector with
three entries representing the amplitude
for any one of the three states of the
spin
supposing you want to rotate that
spin well to rotate that spin you must
multiply it by some kind of rotation
some sort of operator that rotates
it rotate the rotate the spin State it's
got three states the
rotation matrices or the rotation
operators which act on the state Vector
to mix up the components must also be a
three-dimensional representation of the
rotation group in fact it's just that
rot it's just
that so it's often one speaks about spin
one particles being Vector
particles what that means is that the
three states can be thought of as being
in one to one
correspondence with the three components
of a vector and they mix up among
themselves the same way as the
components of the quantum states of of a
spin one particle
but but I want to I'm interested now in
a spin a half
particle supp I have a spin a half
particle and I want to know how the
state do anybody want to take a rest
let's take a little rest yeah we've gone
through a lot of material I've tried to
keep it as simple as I possibly
can incidentally we we've encountered
two different kinds of
groups uh discret groups and continuous
groups the group
of composed of one and P has only two
elements only two elements to the group
and it's sort of discret uh you can
either Flip or not flip that's all there
is the rotation group or the
multiplication by e to the II is
continuous fi can be a continuous
variable so there's a continuous
Infinity of elements
and of course in the rotation group
there are also a continuous uh infinity
of
elements so the kind of Transformations
and the kind of symmetries that we can
think about in physics break up into two
kinds the discrete symmetries and the
continuous
symmetries rotation being a continuous
symmetry reflection uh being a discret
symmetry the groups that are associated
with symmetries are usually called Le
groups l i
e they were first studied in mathematics
by by mathematician named Lee but L
German mathematician in I guess in the
19th
century
um right our interest will mainly be in
continuous groups although now and then
we might uh think of
a uh a discret
group okay um where were we yeah I said
that for a spin one particle which has
three states the mathematics of rotating
around those States is just the
mathematics of the three-dimensional
representation of the rotation group but
then you can ask what about spin a half
particles well first of all what about
spin zero particles what happens to a
spin spin zero when you rotate it
nothing there's that so the uh the
Symmetry group as applied to a spin zero
particle the rotation group really only
has one element and it's the unit
element and nothing else and its
representation it's just completely
represented by nothing more than the
unit operator it's a completely trivial
system the spin zero particle the spin a
half particle also already has two
states now given a state of the spin a
half particle how do what does it mean
to be given a state it
means one Z that's to be identified with
up and
01 is to be identified with down and a
general Quantum state has a complex
number here
uh let's call it alpha 1 and Alpha 2 two
complex numbers what do we specify about
them we specify nothing more than that
the sums
of the squared magnitude of them Alpha
One Star alpha 1 plus Alpha 2 Star Alpha
2 should be equal to one that's all
other than that it's free to uh uh to uh
to choose alpha 1 and Alpha
2 if we choose Alpha 1al 1 and Alpha 2
equal to zero then we are talking about
a spin pointing in the up Direction now
up of course is relative to some
definition of an axis but let's pick our
axis vertical
z-axis then this state represents an up
spin this state represents a down Spin
and in general this combination here
represents a spin state in some
direction spin oriented in some
Direction which is determined by alpha 1
and Alpha 2 now we're not going to do
the algebra figuring all that out but we
can ask what if we take a
given spin
State alpha 1 and Alpha
2 and we rotate it we or do we just
rotate our coordinates or we physically
rotate all the spin States right we
physically rotate the spin to another
axis or just whatever the whatever the
configuration was we rotate it what do
we
get well we have to operate on this to
get something
new Alpha 1 Prime Alpha 2
Prime what do we operate
on states to get new States we operate
with operators or with matrices again
matrices in The Matrix representation
so this is going to be some element
let's call it U u11 u12 u21
[Music]
u22 okay every
rotation can be represented as a 2X two
Matrix acting on Spinners on half spin
States let's see what the properties of
such a
Matrix now this is just another
representation of the rotation group and
it's a 2X two
representation there's a subtlety about
about this which I'm not going to get
into but uh about some of you may know
it that the two valness of these
representations not important is this
this is going to represent a rotation of
the components of a spinner of a half
spin particle when you rotate the the
directions of space all right so what's
the first thing that's important well
first of all when
you act on a state you should get
another state if a state is
characterized by the sums of the squares
of the elements being equal to
one right what does that mean that means
alpha 1 star alpha 1 plus Alpha 2
Star Alpha
2 equals 1 then the same should be true
after rotation
so this should equal well first of all
it should be equal one but it should
also equal alpha 1 Prime Star alpha 1
prime plus dot dot dot plus the same
thing for
two well it's very much or are similar
in pattern to the fact that the sums of
the squares of the components of a
vector should be conserved under a
rotation the only difference is here
we're dealing with complex numbers here
the halfs spin system is described in
terms of complex components
here incidentally let's count
components
um if uh
yeah how many components does it take to
pick a
direction two right how many independent
uh components are there
here four four four they're complex
numbers and each pair of them but we
always know we don't care about the
phase of these things the phase of them
doesn't
matter so dividing through by the phase
and forgetting by the overall
phase that cuts it down to three there
only really three independent numbers
describing uh such a uh spinner but what
else do we
require alpha 1 star Alpha 1 plus and
that's one
equation so really there are only two
independent things here two independent
uh things even though there are four
complex numbers one of the uh parameters
doesn't matter the overall phase it
never affects anything and the other is
the length of the vector the sums of the
squares of the of the of them are always
set equal to one so given any pair of
components or given any spinner like
this there's always some direction that
it's polarized in that it's along that
that its axis is along but how do you
what are the rotation what are the
rotation operators U well they first of
all the most important thing and the
only important thing really is that they
have to preserve the length of Any Given
Vector not the length in
three-dimensional space but the length
meaning the total probability here that
gives rise to a very very similar
condition to
this over
here it gives rise to a condition which
is very similar to R transpose time Ral
1 I'm not going to work it out now you
can work it out yourselves it's the
condition that you transpose complex
conjugate time
U is equal to
1 it's just an extra little complex
conjugate conjugate
because when we sum things we sum them
multiplying by their complex
conjugate this combination here the
transpose complex conjugated is called
the Herm Mission conjugate and it's
represented by UD dagger so we've seen
that before UD dagger UD
dagger is equal to the transpose complex
conjugated
transpose means you flip things about
the main
diagonal complex conjugate you just
complex conjugate every element UD
dagger is equal to U
transpose I wrote it here I don't need
to write it again so UD dagger time
U is equal to
one right so and in fact that's all
we're really going to need there is a 2X
two representation of rotations in
space they're complex matrices and
they're unitary this is the condition
for a unitary Matrix how many components
does a unitary Matrix
have can you figure that
out well every every it's a complex
Matrix eight real components right eight
real components four complex components
but no not quite I mean now there
there's a bunch of relationships here
now how many relationships is
this I heard the right answer four why
is it four because this is a matrix
equation and there's
a com and there's a a separate equation
for each component there are four
components this is four real equations
here four real yeah four real equations
and so there
are four real equations among eight
unknowns there are four independent
parameters of a unitary 2x2
matrix now that's one too many because
we've already found that rotations how
many parameters characterize the
rotation three the direct the unit
Vector which is two and the angle was
three so there's one too many
components here one too many uh degrees
of freedom to actually describe the
rotation group but there was an
obvious candidate for a um for one more
well I don't know how obvious it is but
there was a candidate for one more
restriction that we can put on these
unitary matrices which will cut the
number of parameters by one
more and that is to set the determinant
of them equal to
one okay why the determinant well
um first of all you can see
that the the determinant of the product
of two matrices is just the product of
the
determinants right determinant of a *
determinant of B is the determinant of a
* B so if we were to set the determinant
of every U
equal to one then at least that would be
consistent because when we multiply two
U's together to get another U we would
still have the determinant equal to one
so it is actually a theorem this is very
easy to prove you can prove this this is
a oneliner basically that if you were to
take only the matrices the unitary
matrices which have determinant one that
they form a closed
group right setting the determinant
equal to one does not destroy the group
property simply because first of all the
unit operator has determinant
one and since the product of
determinants is the determinant of the
product there still is a product
structure to the group so one additional
equation that one can impose without
destroying the group property let's just
write it as determinant of U determinant
I'll indicate by a pair of brackets like
that is equal to one
it's also true that the determinant of
UD dagger is equal to one they're
complex conjugates of each
other so the group of unitary matrices
2x two unitary matrices with the
property that every determinant is equal
to one is first of all a three parameter
group it has the same number of
parameters as the rotation group in fact
it is the rotation group uh there's a
subtlety there which I won't get into it
is the rotation group it has the same
multiplication table as the rotation
group it is the rotation group
uh but it doesn't act on vectors it acts
on the states of a spin a half
system so we've discovered something
we've discovered that there are 2 by two
representations of the rotation group
nice question yeah the determinant of
the U dagger is is the same as the no
it's a complex conjugate of it if if
it's not
one If U if if U is not one it's a
complex conjugate yeah but if you have
the equation U dagger U equals
I then I mean ignoring the the
determinant
condition that says the determinant of U
time the determinant of U dagger is one
that's says the determinant of U dagger
to oneus no it has to be it can be e to
the I Theta and e to the minus I Theta
okay yeah okay but now we have fixed it
we have fixed it so that the determinant
is equal to
one all right the
group all right definition the group of
n byn unitary
matrices is called u
n
the a special case is one by one unitary
matricies that's U1 that's the thing up
there right the group of
unitary matrices with determinant one is
called the special unitary
group s n s n special unitary
group it plays an enormous role in
physics
s
n special unitary n byn matrices okay so
this group here which acts on the two
components of a spinner is
su2 that's su2 let's go one step further
before we turn to
quirks one step further is everybody
happy with this yeah I just wondering
where the spin matricies that we
discussed last semester would come in
here the spin matrices the sigmas you're
talking about the sigas SX
with s y i s yeah yeah okay so yeah that
is a good question I will tell you I'll
tell you right now then okay good let's
let's do that right
now all
right there were the matrices
s 1 two and
three and they were actually just half
the poly Matrix
I'll assume you remember what the poly
matrices are okay
um think about group elements which are
very close to the identity that means
rotations by very small
angles rotations by very very small
angles The Operators or the matrices
should be very close to the unit
operator
right right so so we should be able to
write those the special case of uh of
small
rotations we should be able to write
them as having unitary matrices which
are close to one one plus something
small and then the indicate small let's
put an Epsilon there Epsilon times some
Matrix
okay Epsilon time some
Matrix uh let's first ask what is the
condition
that uh yeah now we want to know what's
the condition that U is
unary all right so let's find out let's
multiply U * UD
dagger UD dagger this is not V this is
UD dagger let's multiply it by UD
dagger 1 +
Epsilon M dager the hermiss conjugate of
one is just one I'm taking Epsilon well
let's see we'll take Epsilon to be uh to
be real for the moment Let It Be it's
just a small number it's just a small
number to indicate
smallness uh anything complex can go
into these M's here and this is going to
be 1 plus M
dagger and this should be equal to
one all right when we multiply this out
I'll only keep things to linear order in
epsilon we're going to drop things to
quadratic order in epsilon and that says
that Epsilon
m + m dagger is equal to
Z we have 1 * 1 over here which cancels
this
one quadratic things we don't care about
we have Epsilon M plus M dagger is equal
to zero since the one's
cancelled in other words what it says is
that whatever m is it should be
minus its hermiss con
ugate okay now if we this is called
anti-
hermiss the thing which has this
property is called antih hermiss can we
make something hermiss out of something
that's anti-
hermiss let multiply it by I let's so
let's think about putting an i in here
let's go from the beginning and put an i
in here what do we do over here minus I
her Mission conjugation always involves
uh complex conjugation among other
things
if we did that then we would get M minus
M dagger equal Z because of this
relative minus sign and then we would
find that m equals m dagger in other
words if we incorporated an i into the
definition here then M would be Herm
Mission m is a Herm Mission 2x two
Matrix right it's a Herm Mission 2x2
matrix how many her Mission 2x2 matrices
are there how do you make a her Mission
2x2 matrix oh something else what about
uh the determinant what's the condition
that the
determinant is equal to
1 uh this is a little trickier
um yeah what is the condition oh oh oh I
know mhm okay
yeah let's just write this in the
following way it's
1+ I Epsilon
M minus M dagger and then order Epsilon
squared so let's forget order Epsilon
squar this is the determinant of one
plus a small Matrix do you know what the
uh determinant of one plus a small
Matrix
is anybody
know it is one plus a small number the
question is what is a small number
e to something could you approximate
well you could you could do that it's
easier than that though um yeah let's
let's look at let's do it one one and
then a small Matrix plus M1 uh plus
M11 plus uh
M12
um
M21 and 1 +
M22 I I haven't put the Epsilon in okay
but we'll just treat M as a small thing
let M be a small thing all right what's
the determinant the determinant is this
time this minus this time
this this times this is quadratic in
small
numbers it doesn't matter M11 * M22 is
quadratic in small numbers but there is
a piece here which is 1 * M22 + M11 * 1
what is that that's M11 plus
M22 trace the trace of M the trace of M
so the determinant of one plus a small
Matrix is uh is basically just the trace
of the small
Matrix okay
so yeah the M's have to the the bottom
line is the M's have to be traceless
yeah the bottom line is the M's have to
be traceless that's uh that's uh that we
can prove all right so we have we have
to construct a Herm
Mission
small Matrix which is
traceless that's exactly what these
sigmas are they are the
traceless 2x two hermiss matrices any
traceless 2x2 hermiss matrix can be
written as a sum of Sigma
matrices so these M's here are simply
linear combinations of the
sigmas the particular linear combination
that you choose will depend on the axis
of rotation if you want to make a small
rotation about the x- axis you'll put
Sigma X here if you want to make a small
rotation about the y axis you put Sigma
y there and so forth if you want to make
a small rotation about a linear
combination of the X and Y AIS in other
words a
45° you'll put the linear combination
that's the connection between the sigmas
and the rotation matrices
they're the representations of the small
rotations okay the last thing is how to
combine you know what I think I'm going
to wait uh till next week to talk about
combining representations and just jump
to quirks let's get off the mathematics
for a moment or two we only have a
moment or two uh so let's talk about
quirks
and now we're not interested in the spin
of
quirks well we are interested in the
spin of quirks it's spin a half but
we're not uh that's not what we're
talking about now I'm interested in the
color of
quarks and the color of quarks is
described by a three-state system red
green or blue so if I had a single Quark
that Quark could be in one of three
states just as a spin could be in one of
two states the Quark color can either be
red green or blue and so we could
describe the state of a quark by three
entries the two three entries will
correspond to red green and blue but you
know an alpha 1 and Alpha 2 and Alpha 3
and the sum the squares of Alphas will
just be the probability that it's a red
Quark a green Quark or a blue
quark and
what are the possible symmetries oh and
another thing we can say let me just go
one step further and say we could also
think of the three
Fields the field operator for a red
Quark the field operator for a green
quark and the field operator for a blue
quark and assemble them also in a vector
like
this what kind of symmetries can we
imagine
among the three
quarks we can imagine first of all
certain discret symmetries we can
imagine the discret symmetries which
interchange them interchange red and
green or interchange green and blue or
so forth but we can imagine a larger
family that includes that
incidentally
these rotation matrices here happen to
include the Matrix 1
one this Matrix here is a special
unitary Matrix so among these rotation
matrices is a matrix which interchanges
up and
down this means that the interchange
group is a
subgroup of the full rotation group
happens to be a rotation
deter uh I think we have to put an i in
there somewhere don't we yeah we have to
put an into
uh
yeah uh yeah yeah um that's
right yeah to give it a determinate
one that's right so the permutation of
two things is a special case is a
special case of rotations it's not uh
it's all
right is there anything more complicated
that we could do yeah there is the more
complicated thing we can imagine is
unitary oper now it's not obvious that
there is such a symmetry in nature well
I will tell you there is such a symmetry
in nature and in fact it's the whole
point of having color here is that it
adds another symmetry to physics
important symmetry that symmetry will uh
will play a very important role in the
properties of quantum
chromodynamics but the Symmetry is the
multiplication of the three components
red green and blue by special unitary
3x3
matrices right same mathematics as
appeared here except the mathematics
involves 3x3
matrices I won't fill in all the
components but you know it's u11 dot dot
dot dot dot dot dot dot dot 3x3 matrices
special unitary matrices determinant one
again the special that's called the
special that's called
su3 This is the group
su3 now I'll tell you right now from the
start it is believed in fact it's
mathematically absolutely required that
physics is invariant under this su3
operation in other words it's a kind of
mixing up of the quirks with of the
colors of the quirks which is analogous
to the mixing up of the components of up
and down which is also analogous to the
mixing up of the directions the three
directions of space but this is not
ordinary rotations this is special
unitary matrices how many special unary
yeah let's count the number of special
unary matrices let's count the number of
parameters how many parameters to
describe a special unary 3x3
Matrix okay right 18 - 9 - 1 okay where
y 18 you've got uh nine elements nine
complex elements that's
18 okay you have the equations u Daga U
equal 1 there are nine such equations
one for each entry in The Matrix here so
that's 18 - 9 and then we set the
determinant equal to 1 18 - 9 - 1 is 8
independent 8 it's an eight param
group just like the rotation group is a
three parameter group so there's an
eight parameter uh family of
rotations I bet you wonder I bet you're
wondering what that eight has to do with
the fact that there are eight gluons
aren't you yeah it's the same fact yeah
yeah it's the same fact uh but we will
come to
it right why aren't there nine gluons
because we threw away the determinant
that doesn't make any sense at all but
it's true anyway
yep it is it is
true
um yeah so special unitary 3 by3
matrices are a particular representation
of su3 but su3 is the Symmetry group the
basic symmetry group of quantum
chromodynamics and just like Quantum
electrodynamics was invariant under this
operation here and that told us that
only the in the lonian only things with
the same number
of uh size and side daggers can enter
the idea that the lran is invariant
under su3 also has profound consequences
for the structure for the symmetries for
the conservation laws and so the rule is
every possible term in the lran of
quantum chromodynamics of Quark physics
should be invariant under this group
here we'll come back and we'll start to
talk about how you construct Quantum
chromodynamics a little
bit
[Music]
um I think we're probably finished for
tonight I'm I'm certainly
finished I had intended to go a little
bit further tonight and tell you a
little more but I think that was quite a
lot uh and I don't know how many of you
followed how many of you didn't follow
but I hope you at least get the flavor
if not the color of what the
all right okay we'll go a little bit
further with this but then we'll get
back to some things that can be
understood without too much
mathematics for more please visit us at
stanford.edu